Guide to the Edward Wortley Montagu, 1729-1837
Department of Special Collections
Edward Wortley Montagu,
1729-1837
Special Collections M0279
Montagu, Edward Wortley, 1713-1776.
.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Donative purchase, 1976.
Biographical Note
Edward Wortley Montagu (1713-1776), was the only son of the celebrated letter-writer Lady Mary Wortley Montagu, His career was notorious throughout Europe: he had contracted two bigamous marriages, fought at Fontenoy, was one of two represented Britain at Aix-la-Chapelle, sat as Member of Parliament for Huntingdon, acquired a remarkable proficiency in Arabic and other tongues, appeared in London salons dressed in a wig of iron, and then turned Turk. In Egypt from 1762, he met the Danish Consul, John Feroe. and his wife and being attracted to the latter, persuaded Feroe to go to Europe, told Caroline Feroe that her husband had been drowned and married her himself. However, Feroe returned to Egypt and Montagu had to reassure the Roman Catholic Mrs. Feroe that he would adopt her persuasion, which would invalidate her marriage to the Protestant Consul.
Then, pursued by the Dane and accompanied by his secretary, Nathaniel Davison, the couple set off on an enforced honeymoon, following the supposed route of the Exodus to Mt. Sinai and thence to Jerusalem, where Montagu was received into the Church of Rome. Assisted by Davison, he later published an account of this journey for the Royal Society. Davison later became British Consul at Nice and Tangiers, although he still kept up a correspondence with Montagu; while the latter remained some time in Egypt where it is said he married a Nubian girl called Ayesha, by whom he had a son. He ended his days living as a Turk in Padua, declaring to the priest at his deathbed that he died a good Mussulman and repeating to his son, Fortunatus, in Arabic: Elhamdulillah - May God be Praised.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, primarily between Montagu and his secretary, Nathaniel Davison (1764-1779), journals and notebooks, and miscellaneous documents and letters.
Container List
- E.W. MONTAGU TO NATHANIEL DAVISON (1764-74), (31 items) (Folder 1)
  - 1. 1764, Feb. 11.ALS. Antoura., 2 sides.
  - 2. 1764, Feb. 13-15.ALS. [with ND's reply]. Rosetta., 4 sides.
  - 3. 1764. Feb. 15-17.ALS. [with ND's reply]. Rosetta., 4 sides.
  - 4. 1764, March 19.ALS., 2 sides.
  - 5. 1764, March 23.ALS. Rosetta., 2 sides.
  - 6. 1764. May 21.ALS. Damascus., 2 sides.
  - 7. 1764, Oct. 3.ALS. On exhibit, 5/77., 3 sides.
  - 8. 1764, Dec. 30.ALS. [enclosures #9, 10]., 2 sides.
  - 9. 1764, Sept. 17.ALS. [enclosure to #8] [to Marsand in Italian]., 4 sides.
  - 10. 1764, Sept. 17.A cover [to #9]. [to Marsand, Venetian Consul Gen]., 1 side.
  - 11. 1765, Feb. 2.ALS. Antoura., 4 sides.
  - 12-13. fair copies of #11.
  - 14. 1765, March 27.ALS. Beirut., 2 sides.
  - 15. 1765, April 19.ALS. [enclosure #16]. Beirut., 3 sides.
  - 16. N.D.ALS. to Lord Sandwich. [enclosure to #15]., 4 sides.
  - 17. 1766, June 5.ALS., 3 sides.
  - 18. 1766, June.ALS. Pisa., 3 sides.
  - 19. 1766, July 19.ALS. Bagni di Lucca., 3 sides.
  - 20. 1766, Sept. 27.ALS. Venice., 3 sides.
  - 21. 1766, Oct. 20.ALS. Isola in Istria., 2 sides.
  - 22. 1767, Feb. 8.ALS. Ragusa [Dubrovnik]., 3 sides.
  - 23. 1767, Apr. 15.ALS. Zante., 2 sides.
  - 24. 1772, Dec. 21.ALS. Rosetta., 4 sides.
  - 25. 1773, June 21.ALS. Leghorn. [Livorno]., 4 sides.
  - 26. 1773, Aug. 20.ALS. Pisa., 3 sides.
  - 27. 1773, Dec. 8.ALS. Venice., 4 sides.
  - 28. 1774, Feb. 27.ALS. Venice., 2 sides.
  - 29. 1774, Aug. 13.ALS. Venice., 2 sides.
  - 30. 1774, Sept. 23.ALS. Venice., 3 sides.
  - 31. 1774, Oct. 20.ALS. Venice., 1 side.
- E.W. MONTAGU TO NATHANIEL DAVISON (undated), (9 items) (Folder 2)
  - 1. Thursday night. ALS. Pisa., 3 sides.
  - 2. Wednesday evening. ALS., 3 sides.
  - 3. Monkey night. ALS. Pisa., 3 sides.
  - 4. Saturday night. ALS. Pisa., 2 sides.
  - 5. Monday night. ALS. Pisa., 2 sides.
  - 6. ALS., 4 sides.
  - 7. Friday night. ALS. Pisa., 4 sides.
  - 8. ALS., 7 sides.
  - 9. Thursday night. ALS. Pisa., 4 sides.
- E.W. MONTAGU, OUTGOING CORRESPONDENCE, (1 item) (Folder 3)
  - 1. 1765, Feb. 23.ALS. Beirut. To Botrus Aga, Abbot., 2 sides.
- CORRESPONDENCE TO E.W. MONTAGU (1764-66), (5 items) (Folder 4)
  - 1. Grenville, H. [British Amb. to Ottoman Empire]. ALS. Dec. 22, 1764.[enclosure #2]., 4 sides.
  - 2. Feroe, Jens. [Danish Consul to Egypt]. LS. [copy per H.G.]. Dec. 20, 1764.[encl. to #7]., 4 sides.
  - 3. Watson, W. [Royal Society]. LS [copy]. June 12, 1766., 4 sides.
  - 4. Marsand, Gerolamo. [Venetian Consul in Cairo]. DS. Oct. 13, 1764.[passport]., 1 side.
  - 5. Marsand, Gerolamo. [Venetian Consul in Cairo]. DS. Oct. 13, 1764.[ re marriage?]., 3 sides.
- NATHANIEL DAVISON TO E.W. MONTAGU (1764-65), (5 items) (Folder 5)
  - 1. 1764, Feb. 12.L [copy]. Alexandria., 4 sides.
  - 2. 1764, March 23.ALS. Alexandria., 3 sides.
  - 3. 1764, Oct. 8.ALS. Cairo., 6 sides.
  - 4. 1764, Oct. 17.ALS. Cairo., 4 sides.
  - 5. 1765, March 1.ALS. [letter of resignation]., 4 sides.
- N. DAVISON, OUTGOING CORRESPONDENCE (1764-79), (11 items) (Folder 6)
  - 1. Davison, Mary. ALS. April 26, 1763.Port Mahon, Minorca., 4 sides.
  - 2. Davison, Polly. ALS. June 27, 1763.Alexandria., 4 sides.
  - 3. Davison, Polly. ALS. October 1763.Alexandria., 4 sides
  - 4. Davison, William. ALS. Sept. 12, 1764.Cairo., 4 sides.
  - 5. Varsy, William. ALS. Sept. 16, 1764.Cairo. [In French]., 10 sides.
  - 6. [Varsy, William.] Partial A. Draft of #5. [In French.], 3 sides.
  - 7. Varsy, William. ALS. Sept. 23, 1764.Cairo. [In French] w/annot. by G. T[aylor] re transcription., 11 sides.
  - 8. Varsy, William. ALS. Nov. 19, 1764.Cairo. [In French]., 10 sides.
  - 9. [White, William.] (Professor, Wadham College]. AL fragment. [N.D.], 4 sides.
  - 10. White, [ J.]. [Professor, Wadham College]. AL. Oct. 10, 1779., 4 sides.
  - 11. [Adressee unknown - possibly Varsy]. ALS. N.D., 3 sides.
- CORRESPONDENCE to N. DAVISON (1764-66), (7 items) (Folder 7)
  - 1. Breyer, J.. ALS. Nov. 21, 1766.Livorno., 2 sides.
  - 2. Feroe, John. [Danish Consul in Egypt]. ALS. March 24, 1765.Damiata., 3 sides.
  - 3. Feroe, John. [Danish Consul in Egypt]. ALS. April 24, 1765.[Saida?] Seyda., 4 sides.
  - 4. Feroe, John. [Danish Consul in Egypt]. ALS. June 21, 1765.Seyde [ sic - Saida?]., 7 sides.
  - 5. Turnbull, Wm. ALS. May 10, 1764.Malta. [encl. #5]., 7 sides
  - 6. [Enclosure to #5. Greek inscription].
  - 7. White, J. [Professor, Wadham College]. ALS. Aug. 15, 1779.Oxford., 4 sides.
- JOURNALS & NOTEBOOKS, (5 items) (Folder 8)
  - 1. 1764, June 1_.E.W.M. [Sinai, Giza]., 21 pp. illus. 8vo.
  - 2. 1763, August 1_ 1764. August. N.D.Egypt., 116 sides. 8vo. (+4 loose sides].
  - 3. 1764. August. N.D.w/portrait of E.W.N.
  - 4. [1764]. N.D.w/drawing of date palm.
  - 5. 1764. N.D.w/description of Great Pyramid, [2 loose sheets].
- JOURNALS, NOTES AND NOTEBOOKS, (7 items) (Folder 9)
  - 1. 1763, Sept. 30.[Fred. Christ.]. Von Haven. [Lohich eu Arabie H.?]. Suez. [In French, to M. Napollon, Cairo?]., 20 sides.
  - 2. 1763, Jan. 20.Frid. Christ. Von Haven [Lohich eu Arabie H?].
  - 3. Inscriptions copied at Gebel el Mocatib or the Written Written Mountains in the Road to Mt. Sinai., 4 sides.
  - 4. 1764. Relation du Voyage du Mont Sinai. [w/ corrections]. Written by Consul Davison as an Lect from his own journal in the book marked Aug. 1763 to Aug. 1764Egypt., 20 sides.
  - 5. Draft account of Departure from Mount Sinai., 24 sides.
  - 6. Clean copy of #5. w/additional loose inscriptions., 25 sides.
  - 7. Account, presumably to Royal Society of Davison's Egyptian experiences., 8 sides - folio.
- MISCELLANEOUS DOCUMENTS RE N.D. 's MEDICAL CAREER, ETC., (5 items) (Folder 10)
  - 1. 1809, June 16.Last will & testament of N. Davison. 2 sides & codicil dated Nov. 3, 1810., (copy).
  - 2. 1729, June 25.London. DS. [Admission to doctoral standing at London School of Medicine?].
  - 3. 1733, Sept. -.London. DS. [Doctoral degree?].
  - 4. 1729, May 27.DS. [William Frederick, Duke of Gloucester, grants medical license?].
  - 5. 1732, July 3.D. [Wm. Frederick, Duke of Gloucester - similar to above #4].
- MISCELLANY, (9 items) (Folder 11)
  - 1. 1787, Feb. 7.ALS. Sophia of Nieubourg. [Addressee unknown]., 1 side.
  - 2. N.D. Copy of note attached to copy sent to Dr. Yelleroky of letter to Duc de Caulnes - fm. the words `delicate Nature too' - p. 220 of the series of papers sent to Dr. Y., 2 sides.
  - 3. 1837, May 26. List of books illustrative of English History - chiefly Biographical Histories., 4 sides & cover.
  - 4. AD. English historical royal chronology from AD 827-1199., 1 side. folio.
  - 5. A Poem. La Pastorella. [Italian]., 13 sides.
  - 6. A Fragment of Play: Comedia Famosa., 4 sides.
  - 7. A translation from Latin inscription in Kirk [Church] of our blest lady of Laureto. c. 1635., 1 side.
  - 8. A. Epilogue of the Phornoro spoken at Westminster School., 4 sides.
  - 9. A. Fragment of verses re: Sir Isaac Pennington. Stauzas 10-18., 4 sides.